Hello hackers, 欢迎来到pwn college关于内存错误的第二个视频
Hello hackers, welcome to video 2 of the memory error module PWN college.
我是Yan, 然后今天我们会讲一些宏观上会导致内存错误的问题
I am Yan, and today we will be gonna talking about high-level problem that lead to memory error.
在之前的视频里, 我讲过
As a reminder, in the previous video, I talks about how ...uh.
位于右边图片的这个人(Dennis RitChie)创造了C
Dennis Ritchie. This man on the right of the slide here created the C programming language.
他为了在Unix操作系统上的实用程序创造了这个
He create this to create the utilities for the Unix operating system which he had co-created just several years earlier.
C 被设计为一种给开发者提供低层次操作能力的语言
And C was designed to give low-level control and power to the developer to allow them to write fast code
但是一样使用源代码, 高级编程语言, 而不是直接写汇编
but still use a source code, high-level language to write it rather than writing a directly assembly.
不幸的是, 在某种程度上C和冯诺依曼结构结合后
Unfortunately in combination in a way with the von neumann architecture, brought to us with three Johns.
(左边这三个 Johns 带来了冯诺依曼结构)
On these figures on the left.
而且冯诺依曼结构不是很关心安全性
And von neumann architecture (is) kind of seeming thoughtlessness about security.
所以 C 的崛起和快速扩散让我们直到今天都受到内存错误的困扰
The rise and amazing spread of C has let to a state where we are plagued with memory errors of software even now till these days.
所以让我们看看一些导致内存错误的问题
So let look at some high-level problems of these errors that lead to these errors.
总体来说, 最大的问题是C过于相信开发者
The biggest problem, kind of the overall general summary is that C trusts the developer.
在 Python 如果你创建一个3个元素的列表, 然后试图访问第七个元素
In Python if you create a list with three elements in it, and you try to access to the eleventh element.
Python 会阻止你访问, 由于这个列表只有三个元素
Python will tell you: No, this list only has three elements, you are not accessing the eleventh, absolutely no ways!
它会抛出一个异常
It will throw an exception.
然后你会知道你访问了不能访问的东西, 然后去修改代码
And then you will realize: oh, I am accessing an element that I shouldn't be accessing, and you can fix your code.
但是 C 不会也不能这么做
C won't do that. In fact C cannot do that.
C 被设计的尽可能底层
C is designed, again, to be as low-level as as directly translation as possible.
C 只是帮你承担寄存器管理的职责
All C really does, is take the burden of register management away from you.
和相较于汇编很好的调用方法等等
And handle, you know, calling functions and so forth in a nicer way than a assemble may do.
此外你还可以创造结构体之类的, C 能做很多
Who let you create structures and et cetera. Of course, C does a lot.
但是 C 不会隐式追踪有些东西, 比如数组里元素的数量
But what C doesn't do is implicitly track things like the number of elements in an array.
如果你想追踪元素数量和在访问元素前检查是否越界
If you want to track the number of elements in array, and be very careful to check if the array is big enough before you access it.
你当然可以在 C 里这么做
Of course you can write that in C.
你可以创造一个同时有数组和数量的结构
You can create a structure, that has both an array and a size.
但是在现实里, 如果人们不那么做并执意继续访问, C 会允许访问
But realistically, if people do not do that, and they just access memory willy-nilly. C will let them do that.
然后就会引起问题
And a problem will arise.
这个问题也与我们要讨论的其他宏观上的问题有关
The problem that will arise, have to do with some these other high-level problem caused that we will talk about.
让我们从 C 在同一个地方储存控制信息和普通信息开始
To begin with, C mixes control information, and data in the same place.
首先你应该回想一下"栈"
You should remember the "stack".
在之前的逆向工程的课程里, 你应该学到了栈和使用了他
You learned about it and hopefully had to do with a lot in the previous module in reverse engineering.
栈里面有很多用户数据
The stack holds a lot of user data.
我指虽然栈从一开始就存了很多用户数据
I mean those user data actually, the stack start out holding a lot of user data.
但是用户数据在执行过程中散布在各个地方
But user data throughout the execution progress spreads all over the place.
不幸的是, 在同一个地方储存着大量的控制信息
Unfortunately, in those same general memory region, programs, store a lot of control information.
这些控制信息和普通信息(包括用户信息)储存在一起
And they store these together with the non-control data that including user data that they store.
以栈为例子:
Recall the stack, for example.
栈上的所有东西都混杂在一起, 方法在栈上的栈帧中包含了返回地址
Everything on the stack is jumbled together, functions have their function frames on the stack containing the return address.
我们先从左边开始, 首先是这些方法的局部变量. 其中有一部分是由用户控制的
Let's start actually from the left here, the local variables of the active function. Some of which are users controlled.
可能被攻击者控制
potential attacker control :D
然后是储存的一些指向其他地方的指针, 比如栈的基指针指向栈上的某个位置
Saved pointers to other place of memory, for example, the saved base pointer for the stack point elsewhere in the stack.
接下来是方法中储存的指针, 比如用来返回的指针
save pointer to code, pointer that are later used to return from the function
更往右的是调用(这个方法的)方法的局部变量
And further to the right in the stack, further up stack, local variables of the caller function
接下来这个方法的调用者的栈等等, 以此类推, 栈上就有很多数据
the function that called that function, the function that called that function, and so on, there is a lot data on the stack.
这些都储存在一起, 被同等对待
And these all store together and all treated exactly the same.
这些有很大的安全隐患, 还记得之前讨论的访问第数组七个元素吗
which is has serious security implications, earlier we talked about accessing the eleventh element of three elements array.
在 C 里如果 local buffer 是 a 这个数组, 然后如果你那么做
Well, of course, what happened when you do that, in C, if you local buffer is this "a" array.
你会读写到一些东西在那
You end up accessing somewhere in here and writing data directly there.
这是一个坏消息
That, really bad news.
你可以用这个性质做很多事情
What can you with that? You can do a lot with that.
比如你可以改返回地址, 从指向 .text 里某个位置(指硬编码 string)到其他任意位置
You can, for example, take a return address, that was pointing somewhere in the dot text section into the code of the program and change to point somewhere else.
或者你可以注入一些Shell code
Or change to point to some shell code that you injected.
如果你还记得之前讲过的 Shell Code
If you are recall the shell code in module.
这是一个大问题
This is a big problem.
事实上, 这个问题在某一个晴天, 可能是晴天
And in fact, this problem, on one sunny day, probably is the sunny somewhere.
在 1988, Robert Teppan Morris 用这个性质, 一个基于栈的缓冲区溢出
in 1988, Robert Teppan Morris used this exact situation, a stack base buffer overflow.
他通过溢出重写了方法的返回值
He overflowed from some buffer on the stack and overwrote those return address.
他用这个性质做了第一个被记录的利用内存错误的攻击据我所知
He used this to create a first documented memory corruption exploit as far as I know.
启动了第一个蠕虫并摧毁了当时整个互联网
Launched the first designed worm and brought down the entire internet.
我们在讨论 Shell Coding 的时候谈过这一点
We talked about this back when we talked about the shell coding.
但是他就是用了这个性质导致了那些意外的损失
But this is, these are the exact bug that he used to do all these damage, accidentally.
这个损失如此之大以至于当时的互联网宕机, 失去连接
The damage was so great that the internet had to basically shutdown, disconnected.
修复所有的机器后再重新接入
Fixed all the machine and then plugged back in.
想象一下如果现在发生这个事会十分疯狂
Imagine doing that now will be insane.
因为这件事, 由于 1986 年的计算机欺诈和滥用法, 他被定罪
For this, of course, I mentioned before he was convicted under the 1986 computer fraud and abuse act.
但是我没想到的是他后来当上了 MIT 的计算机教授并资助了包括 Y-Combinator 的很多公司
But I didn't mention that he is since become a computer science professor at MIT, and co-funded y combinator and a bunch of other ventures.
虽然他有个不光彩的历史, 但他做的很好
So he is doing quite well, despite he is shady past.
让我们继续看第三个问题
Alright, let's move on to problem three.
C 混合了元数据(metadata)和数据就像它混合了控制信息和普通信息一样
C mixes control data and non-control data. In the same way, C mixes data and metadata.
同样这个也是有问题的, 以 string 为例子
And this is also problematic. very similar but also problematic, consider the simplest example is string.
你应该知道 C 的字符串以空字节(\0)结束
You should all know strings are null terminated in C.
比如当你有个一个内容为 "Yan" 的字符串
When you have a string, you say, you know, the name is Yan.
在这个例子中, 这个字符串是一个10个字节的数组, 拥有一个"Yan"的初始值
In this case, this is a ten character array with initial value of "Yan", holds ten bytes.
"Yan" 加上7个空字节(\0)
"Yan" and then seven NULL bytes.
其中三个字符是数据, 'Y', 'a', 和'n', 剩下的空字节可以当作元数据
Three of these bytes are data, 'Y', 'a' and 'n' and the NULL byte, actually, is meta data.
这些元数据表示了这是这个字符串的结尾
It encodes, it says: hey, this is the end of string.
他用一个(空)字节隐式编码了字符串的长度
This implicitly encodes the size of the string, using just a single byte.
所以这个字符串的长度就是从开头到空字节的位置
And the size of this string is basically the beginning of the string up to where the NULL byte is.
这个是有问题的
This is problematic.
比如当你用标准系统输入作为输入, 你会获得一些数据
Consider if you are just inputting a name using the read system call, then just get a bunch of data.
然后你把输入中的数据输入到这个字符串, 然后用一个宏获得字符串的长度
And you do somethings like read from standard input, into name, and then there are macro give you size of the variable.
这个第一眼看起来很合理
So the size of name, this looks reasonable at first glance.
但是他是有问题的, 首先它允许用户在任何地方输入空字节
But there some problems. First of all, it allows users to inject NULL bytes, anywhere they want.
然后我们会照盘全收下那些数据
We will happy take then.
比如我用空字节替换掉 "Yan" 里的 'a'
So I could a NULL byte instead of the 'a' in "Yan".
这就代表了我输入了一字节长的字符串和一堆其他数据而不是10字节长
And suddenly, instead of ten length string, I have inputted one length string and much of other data.
这个状态不是可靠的
The status of which is questionable, right?
因为任何字符串操作都会在读到空字节结束
Because any string operation will terminate on that NULL byte.
类似的是, 情况会更糟如果字符串不包含任何空字节
Likewise what is if there are no NULL bytes, this even worse.
如果我输入10字节长的有效数据
If I just fill all ten bytes with data.
这个字符串会是多长?
How long is that string?
看见了吗, 这个给我们了一个提示 C 不会存长度数据
See? It raise a reminder, stores no other length information.
在编译后, 它没有任何方法知道长度
It has no way to know that this is, after compiling the code.
它没有任何方法知道这个字符串曾经是 1 0 字 节 长
That no way to know that this used to be ten ~ bytes ~ long.
所以任何操作在这个缺少空字节的字符串上都会十分奇怪和疯狂
Right, so further operation on this variable lacking that NULL bytes that encode is length at the string length might do wired and crazy things.
接下来是最后一个宏观上的问题, 初始化和清理
Alright final high-level problem you covered, initialization and clean up, right.
再重复一遍, C 是非常底层的, 除非你让它初始化, 它就不会初始化
Again, C is very low-level, unless you tell it to, it will not do any initialization.
和任何清理, 全部的清理工作, 比如
Or mostly any clean up, all there will do in term of clean up, for example.
添加栈指针去释放我上节课讨论过的栈帧
Is add to your stack pointer to quote unquote deallocate the stack frame I am talked about in the previous module.
释放栈帧就是清除全部的数据
How deallocating the stack frame that naturally remove any data.
但是在 C 的清理阶段, C 只是移动栈指针然后保留全部的数据
Right in the clean up stages, C just move stack pointer. That all data still there.
只是那些数据都在栈指针的左边了, 所以在概念上来说, 在正常的程序操作中他们不存在, 虽然实际上是存在的
It just now to the left of stack pointer so doesn't real conceptually exists in normal program operation. But it still there.
你有机会可以访问到那些数据
You may still be able to access it.
如果这个程序有内存错误
If there was a memory error in the program.
类似的, C 不会主动初始化任何东西, 除非你告诉它或者显式初始化
Likewise, initialization, C won't initial anything, unless you tell it to, unless you explicitly initialize it.
比如对于这个叫 "my_variable" 的8字节长的数组来说
If you look at this example, there is a character array called "my_variable" and it is of size eight.
当这个方法被调用时, 它的值是什么?
When the function was called, what will be the value of "my_variable".
它不会全是空字节
It won't be NULLs.
比如在上一个例子中, 我们有这个初始化值
In the previous example, I had this, initial value
这个初始化显式初始化了这个字符串在内存中
this is an initialization that explicitly initialize my name to this value in memory.
但是对于现在这个例子来说没有初始值
This has no initial value.
然后我敢说你在 C 写的代码也没有初始化
And I sure that you are created code in C that had no initialization either.
在没有初始化的情况下, 它会拥有之前的方法留下来的在栈的那个位置上的数据
Without initialization, it will simply have the value that happened to be there on the stack, left over by previous function.
你可以去试一下, 创建一个像这样的程序然后运行
You can try it. Create a program like this, run it
然后这个结果我也会在未来的视频里进一步解释
And see what it tell you actually will also go through future video more in depth.
这个也是 C 程序面临的一个主要的问题
But it is a major issue, facing C program.
这些就是4个主要的问题了, 初始化, 元数据, 控制信息
So these are four major problems, initialization, meta data, control data
和让开发者有自己杀自己的能力
And basically the ability of developer to shoot themselves in the foot.
可以写出来一个安全的 C 程序吗? 这是可以的, 因为 C 不是一个不安全的语言
Is possible to write secure C code? Absolutely, it not that C is an insecure language.
只是 C 给你了一些工具, 你可以以不安全的方式用那些工具, 如果你想
C give you the tools to use these in insecure way, if you so wanted it to.
这是一个点我希望你们能明白, 另外一个点是
That kind one take away I like you to take from this course. The other take away are from this module.
从很多例子里可以得出, C 这种底层的语言很容易被错误的使用
The other take away though is in many many cases is very very very very easy to misuse C and other low-level languages.
这会导致写出不安全的代码
In a way, that ends up in the creation of insecure code.
我将在未来的视频里讲更多不同的内存损坏的例子
I will see you in future video so this module will go in depth into a couple of different examples of memory corruption.
字幕: Eritque arcus
来源: pwn.college
在 CC-BY-NC 下发布
2022.12
然后我将讨论内存损坏的应对措施
And then we will talk about mitigations of memory corruption.